Okay, moving on to bone tumors.
The first tumor is an osteoma.
Osteo means bone, and oma means mass.
So this is a benign tumor of bone.
Now there are two high yields for an osteoma.
Number one, it most commonly arises
on the surface of facial bones.
And number two, it's associated with Gardner syndrome.
Now recall from our GI lecture
that Gardner syndrome is familial adenomatous polyposis
plus fibromatosis in the retroperitinium,
and again, fibromatosis is a non-neoplastic
proliferation of fibroblasts that grows
and locally destroys tissue.
And then number three, osteomas of the facial bone.
And so here we're talking about those osteomas
that are associated with Gardner syndrome.
So that's particularly high yield for board examinations.
Osteoid osteoma is a benign tumor of osteoblasts.
Remember that osteoblasts are the cells that lay down bone,
but they don't make bone.
They make something called osteoid.
And osteoid is a matrix that gets mineralized,
and when it gets mineralized with calcium and phosphate,
then it becomes bone.
And so this tumor produces osteoid,
and in response to this osteoid,
so imagine this is the osteoid here,
you get a rim of sclerotic sort of reactive bone,
and that's what's called the osteoma.
So basically here is the osteoid,
and here this rim is the osteoma.
So let's read this now.
So this is a benign tumor of osteoblasts,
which make osteoid,
surrounded by a rim of reactive bone,
hence the term osteoma.
It occurs in the cortex of young adults,
less than 25 years of age,
which is sort of the classic demographic,
and it arises in the cortex of long bones.
Now let's go back and remind ourselves
that the bone has a cortex,
which is its surface,
and then there's a medulla.
And so this tumor is going to arise
on the cortex of the bone,
and also important to note
is that it usually arises
on the diaphysis in a long bone.
So for example,
if this is the growth plate,
then above the growth plate
is called the epiphysis.
The growth plate region
is called the metaphysis,
and this long shaft here
is called the diaphysis.
And so osteoid osteoma
usually occurs on the cortex
of a long bone
in the region of the diaphysis.
Now the presentation is also important,
and that is that the patients have bone pain,
but it resolves with aspirin.
And examiners really like you to know
that in an osteoid osteoma,
the bone pain resolves with aspirin.
Now when imaging is performed,
you'll see a bony mass
with a radiolucent core.
Again, the idea here
is that you've got
a center core of osteoid,
which will be radiolucent.
It won't get picked up on the x-ray.
However, that will be surrounded
by a rim of reactive bone,
which will light up as white on the x-ray,
i.e. the color of bone.
And so that's what we mean here
when we say that you get a bony mass
with a radiolucent core.
The bony mass represents the rim,
and the center, the core,
represents the osteoid.
Now osteoblastoma is a benign tumor of osteoblast.
It's very similar to osteoid osteoma
because that was also a benign tumor of osteoblast.
However, there are three key differences
that are very high yield.
Osteoblastoma is larger.
An osteoid osteoma is usually less than two centimeters,
and osteoblastoma is usually greater than two centimeters.
The osteoblastoma usually arises in the vertebra.
Remember that the osteoid osteoma arose on the cortex
of the diaphysis of long bones.
And number three, an osteoblastoma presents as bone pain
that does not respond to aspirin, very high yield.
Whereas with an osteoid osteoma,
the bone pain would respond to aspirin.
Osteochondroma is a benign tumor of bone
with an overlying cartilage cap.
It's the most common benign tumor of bone,
and it arises from a lateral projection of the growth plate.
Now let's illustrate this.
Here is the bone.
This is the growth plate.
And recall that the growth plate is made of cartilage.
Now as the growth plate expands,
it will then result in the elongation of the bone,
producing linear growth.
Now imagine if you had a lateral projection
of the growth plate like this,
then that would then subsequently result in,
for example, a projection of bone
with a surface of cartilage on it
that would look like this,
because this here would actually also grow,
but it would grow this way.
And so this then results in the tumor osteochondroma.
So again, if this was the tumor here,
the bone here represents the osteo,
and this cartilage cap that came
from that lateral projection of the growth plate
represents the chondro,
and the oma represents the mass,
so osteochondroma.
Here's a picture of an osteochondroma.
This entire thing represents the osteochondroma.
Imagine that it would be coming off
the surface of bone here.
So again, what would have happened
is you had a lateral projection
of the growth plate.
The lateral projection of the growth plate
will then grow,
and when it grows,
you'll get a surface of cartilage.
Notice this white here represents the cartilage,
underlying which would be bone,
and this represents bone.
And one of the important things
is that this will normally be contiguous
with the marrow space of the bone
from which it's growing.
So if this was the bone from which it's growing,
it'll attach and be contiguous
with the marrow space,
and that's also very important
considering an osteochondroma.
Now the final point
is that overlying cartilage
on the top of the osteochondroma
can transform into a malignant cartilage tumor,
and that would be called a chondrosarcoma,
and that's particularly important as well.
Osteosarcoma is a malignant tumor of bone.
Osteo means bone,
and sarcoma means malignant mesenchymal tumor.
And of course,
it's the osteoblasts that make bone,
and so the proliferation is actually
of the osteoblast.
Now the peak incidence is seen in teenagers,
but less commonly,
it can also be seen in the elderly.
Here's a graph of the peak incidence,
so here is the teenagers,
and here are the elderly.
Of course, this would be the incidence.
Now it's important to note
that some of the risk factors
that lead to osteosarcoma
include familial retinoblastoma.
Familial retinoblastoma,
recall from our neoplasia lectures,
leads to an increased risk
for biolateral retinoblastoma
and osteosarcoma,
particularly high yield.
And that would be something
that would lead to risk within teenagers.
In addition,
we have a peak here with the elderly,
and there are two very high yield risk factors
to be aware of.
Number one is Paget's disease of bone.
Recall that when we talked
about Paget's disease of bone,
I told you that it normally occurs
at the age of 60,
and I also told you
that one of the complications
was osteosarcoma.
And do you remember
the second complication?
The second complication was
high output cardiac failure.
But anyway,
Paget's disease of bone
has an increased risk
for osteosarcoma.
And the second important thing
that leads to an increased risk
in the elderly
would be radiation.
So radiation exposure
would increase the risk
within the elderly.
Osteosarcoma classically arises
in the metaphysis of long bones.
Again, here's a picture of bone.
You've got a growth plate here.
And so what's above the growth plate
is called the epiphysis.
The region of the growth plate
is called the metaphysis.
And this long shaft here
is called the diaphysis.
So osteosarcoma
normally occurs
in the metaphysis.
And that's particularly high yield
for board exams.
Now, it'll usually occur
in the long bone.
Classically, the distal femur
or the proximal tibia,
so around the region of the knee.
It can present
as pathologic fracture,
which basically means
that the tumor weakens the bone.
which then makes the bone
susceptible to fracture,
i.e. the fracture occurs
because there's some sort of pathology
underlying in the bone.
Or it can present
with bone pain with swelling.
In either case,
an x-ray would be performed.
And this is the classic finding
that would be seen on x-ray.
Here you can see
that there's a destructive lesion
growing within the bone.
This represents osteosarcoma.
And one of the high yield things
that examiners like to know
is that osteosarcoma,
as it begins to grow
and expand the bone
and eventually go into
the adjacent soft tissue,
one of the things
that it will do
is that it will drag
the periosteum,
which is a layer
of connective tissue
attached to the bone,
off the bone.
So imagine here,
if this is the surface of bone
and it's covered
with periosteum,
you can clearly see
that here,
the periosteum
is being lifted
off the bone.
Now that creates
an angle right here
called Codman's angle.
And board examiners
like you to know
that Codman's angle
is a sign of osteosarcoma.
In addition,
with osteosarcoma,
sometimes you can see
this hazy radio opacity
coming from the tumor,
which almost looks like
the burst of sunlight
coming off the horizon.
It's not very well
illustrated in this image.
It basically represents
the tiny fragments of bone
being produced
by the osteosarcoma.
If a biopsy was performed,
the key finding would be
large pleomorphic cells,
i.e. high-grade malignant cells,
that are producing
this pink matrix
called osteoid.
Again, pleomorphic cells
that are producing osteoid
is the hallmark on biopsy.
Giant cell tumor
is a tumor comprised
of multinucleated giant cells
and stromal cells.
It occurs in young adults.
One of the very high-yield points
is that it arises
in the epiphysis.
Now, of course,
this is the diaphysis,
and here is the metaphysis,
and up here is the epiphysis.
Now, this is very important
because it's the only tumor
that you need to know
that's going to arise
in the epiphysis.
And so on board exam,
if you have an epiphyseal tumor,
that's basically
giant cell of bone.
It usually arises
in the distal femur
or the proximal tibia
around the knee,
and it's kind of similar
in location
to osteosarcoma, actually.
Now, on x-ray,
you'll see something called
the soap bubble appearance,
and the idea here
is this is the diaphysis,
and then this is the metaphysis,
and up here is the epiphysis.
You get the tumor growing,
and in response to the tumor,
you get a little bit
of reactive bone formation
circling the tumor,
and a bunch of these
little areas of bone
reacting against the tumor form,
and so it produces
these bubbles
that look like soap bubbles
in the epiphysis.
So, soap bubbles in the epiphysis
is giant cell tumor of bone.
This is a locally aggressive tumor
that may recur.
Ewing sarcoma
is a malignant proliferation
of poorly differentiated cells
derived from neuroectoderm.
Board examiners like you to know
that Ewing sarcoma
is derived from neuroectoderm.
It arises in the diaphysis
of long bones,
usually in male children,
so basically it would be here,
and it grows inside
the medullary cavity.
Now, as it grows
inside the medullary cavity,
it is then going to push
on the surface of the bone,
and as it pushes
you're going to get layering
of new bone by the periosteum.
Remember that the periosteum
is a connected tissue
that surrounds the bone,
and it also has the ability
to produce new bone.
In fact, when you get a fracture,
for example,
it's the periosteum
that forms the new bone.
And so, as you put pressure
on the surface of this bone
with the tumor growing in it,
the periosteum will begin
to lay down layers of new bone.
Now, those layers of new bone
will have an onion skin
appearance on x-ray.
Imagine if you looked
at the bone head-on,
you would see sort of
an onion skin layer,
another layer,
as the periosteum
is being laid down,
trying to protect the bone
from this tumor
that's growing inside.
And these cells
resemble lymphocytes.
And that's very important
because it can be confused
with two things.
Number one,
it could be confused
with lymphoma.
And number two,
it can be confused
with chronic osteomyelitis.
Now, one of the interesting
things about Ewing sarcoma
is that some patients
can present with fever.
Now, imagine if you have
a patient that has swelling
of the bone
and has fever,
one of the things
that you're going to think
about is osteomyelitis.
So, it can be confused
with number one,
lymphoma,
or number two,
osteomyelitis.
And what I clearly distinguish
these cells from both lymphoma
and osteomyelitis
is the fact that
these cells
have an 11-22 translocation.
And that 11-22 translocation
is particularly high yield
for Ewing sarcoma.
Ewing sarcoma is fairly aggressive
and it often presents
with metastasis,
but it also responds well
to chemotherapy.
Moving on to cartilage tumors,
let me just highlight
a couple simple principles
that will make this discussion
very easy.
Number one,
cartilage tumors
can be benign or malignant.
Benign cartilage tumor,
chondroma,
a malignant cartilage tumor
is called a chondrosarcoma.
Number two,
cartilage tumors arise
in the medulla.
So, remember that
when you have bone,
you have a cortex
and you have a medulla,
cartilage tumors normally
arise in the medulla.
Number three,
benign tumors,
i.e. chondroma,
they occur in the small bones
of the hands and the feet.
And malignant tumors,
i.e. chondrosarcoma,
occur centrally
in the pelvis
or the central skeleton.
And those are the key take-homes.
Now let's read together.
So, chondroma
is a benign tumor of cartilage.
It arises in the medulla.
Cartilage tumors
normally arise in the medulla.
And because it's benign,
it'll be in the small bones
in the hands and the feet.
Here's a picture
of the tubular
or small bones
of the hands.
And you can clearly see
that there's this mass
growing in the medullary space.
And again,
this represents a chondroma.
Chondrosarcoma
is a malignant
cartilage-forming tumor.
Again,
because it's a cartilage tumor,
it usually arises
in the medulla.
But in this particular case,
it'll be in the medulla
of the pelvis
or the central skeleton.
And so these are
some of the basic high yields
concerning cartilage-forming tumors.
The final discussion
involves metastatic tumors.
Metastatic tumors
are more common
than primary tumors
in the bone.
They usually result
in osteolytic lesions
or punched-out lesions
of the bone.
However,
one important high-yield exception
is prostate cancer.
This usually produces
an osteoblastic lesion.
And so what that means
is that when you look
at the bone,
instead of having this
punched-out circular space,
as would occur
in osteolytic lesions,
in an osteoblastic lesion,
you get activation
of the osteoblast,
and they begin
to lay down bone
adjacent to the tumor,
and that gives you
sclerosis of the bone.
And so again,
prostate carcinoma
classically produces
osteoblastic lesions.
And that concludes
our discussion
of bone tumors.